Finding Aid for Harlan Henthorne Hatcher Papers
Bentley Historical Library
- University of Michigan Presidency
  - Ceremonial/Public Role as President
    The Ceremonial/Public Role as President (4.7 linear ft.; 1951-1967) is a smaller series pertaining to Hatcher's inaugural, his engagement (or invitation) files, his speeches as president, and the files accumulated from the travels he made as president.
    - Inauguration, November 27, 1951
      - Correspondence, committee reports, invitations, etc., 19 folders (Box 54)
    - Engagements-Invitations-accepted (correspondence)
      - Alumni, July 1961-June 1962 (Box 55)
      - Commencement, July 1961-June 1962 (Box 55)
      - General, July 1961-June 1962 (Box 55)
      - Operation Michigan, 1961-1962 (Box 55)
      - University/Student Groups, July 1961-June, 1962 (Box 55)
      - Alumni, July 1962-June 1963 (Box 55)
      - Commencement, July 1962-June, 1963 (Box 55)
      - General, July 1962-June 1963 (Box 55)
      - University/Student Groups, July 1962-June 1963 (Box 55)
      - Alumni, July 1963-June 1964 (Box 55)
      - Commencement, July 1963-June 1964 (Box 55)
      - General, July 1963-June 1964 (Box 55)
      - Operation Michigan, 1963-1964 (Box 55)
      - University/Student Groups, July 1963-June 1964 (Box 55)
      - Alumni, July 1964-June 1965 (Box 55)
      - Commencement, July 1964-June 1965 (Box 55)
      - General, July 1964-June 1965 (Box 55)
      - Operation Michigan, 1964-1965 (Box 55)
      - University/Student Groups, July 1964-June 1965 (Box 55)
      - University of Michigan Capsule Review, 1964-1965 (Box 55)
      - Alumni, July 1965-June 1966 (Box 55)
      - Commencement, July 1965-June 1966 (Box 55)
      - General, July 1965-June 1966 (Box 55)
      - University/Student Groups, July 1965-June 1966 (Box 55)
      - University of Michigan Capsule Review, 1965-1966 (Box 55)
      - Alumni, July 1966-June 1967 (Box 55)
      - Commencement, July 1966-June 1967 (Box 55)
      - General, July 1966-June 1967 (Box 55)
      - University/Student Groups, July 1966-June 1967 (Box 55)
      - Alumni, July-December 1967 (Box 55)
      - Commencement, July-December 1967 (Box 55)
      - General, July-December 1967 (Box 55)
      - University/Student Groups, July-December 1967 (Box 55)
    - Speeches, September 1951-November 1967; 1971
      - 1951
        - State Bar of Michigan, "Change with Stability", September 26, 1951 (Box 56)
      - The Economic Club of Detroit, "Can We Humanize the Robots?", October 15, 1951
        - Inaugural Address, November 27, 1951 (Box 56)
        - Land-Grant Colleges & Universities, "Colleges, Universities, and the State,", November 14, 1951 (Box 56)
        - Unidentifiable, November 16, 1951 (Box 56)
        - Modern Language Association of America, "The Pure Flame,", December 28, 1951 (Box 56)
        - Board in Control of Intercollegiate Athletics, "Statement by Harlan Hatcher, President,", December 31, 1951 (Box 56)
      - 1952
        - Michigan State Society, Washington, January 26, 1952 (Box 56)
        - New York U-M Alumni, February 8, 1952 (Box 56)
        - Michigan College Foundation Flint & WUOM, February 18, 1952 (Box 56)
        - Brotherhood Week, February, 1952 (Box 56)
        - State of Michigan, Lansing, MI, "Address to Legislature,", March 19, 1952 (Box 56)
        - Religious Affairs & Student Pastors, March 31, 1952 (Box 56)
        - Clements Library Meeting, April 1, 1952 (Box 56)
        - Rotary, April 21, 1952 (Box 56)
        - Honors Convocation, Natural Resources, April 22, 1952 (Box 56)
        - Dean Charles Odegaard, Welcome, April 1952; 1952 (Box 56)
        - Rutgers University, President Lewis W. Jones Inauguration, May 8, 1952 (Box 56)
        - Law School, University of Michigan, June 26, 1952 (Box 56)
        - International Association of Insurance Counsel, "Change With Stability,", June, 1952 (Box 56)
        - Ford Motor Company Fund, "The Great Adventure,", July 1, 1952 (Box 56)
        - School of Banking, University of Wisconsin, "Commerce and American Culture,", September 5, 1952 (Box 56)
        - Michigan Municipal League, "The Importance of Education for the Public Service,", September 24, 1952 (Box 56)
        - Michigan Education Association, Detroit, "The Mid-Twentieth Century American Scholar,", October 24, 1952 (Box 56)
        - Michigan State College, November 4, 1952 (Box 56)
        - Grand Rapids Rotary, "Higher Education speech,", December 4, 1952 (Box 56)
        - Commencements, General, 1952 (Box 56)
        - Association of American Medical Colleges, 63rd Annual Meeting, 1952 (Box 56)
      - 1953
        - Speech Conference, February 18, 1953 (Box 56)
        - 1953 Symposium, "State University of New York: Its Progress and Its Prospects," March 20-21, 1953 (Box 56)
        - Michigan Savings and Loan League Clinic, University of Michigan, "Words of Welcome,", March 24, 1953 (Box 56)
        - Sigma Xi, May 13, 1953 (Box 56)
        - Ferris Institute Commencement, May 25, 1953 (Box 56)
        - National Association of State Universities, May, 1953 (Box 56)
        - School Board Members, September 24, 1953 (Box 56)
        - University of Texas Inauguration of Logan Wilson, "The Role of the State University in Higher Education in the Second Half of the Twentieth Century,", October 29, 1953 (Box 56)
      - 1954
        - American Drug Manufacturers Association, "Between Two Worlds,", June 28-July 1, 1954 (Box 56)
        - "Woman in a Man's World" (Box 56)
      - 1955
        - Association of American Colleges, "The Faith that Moves Mountains,", January 12, 1955 (Box 56)
        - Detroit Athletics Club, "A College President Looks at Athletics,", January 26, 1955 (Box 56)
        - Canada-United States Conference on Mutual Relations, "The Canadian-American Community of Interest in Social and Educational Affairs,", February 7-8, 1955 (Box 56)
        - Michigan State College Founders Day, "Greetings from the Michigan Public Institutions of Higher Education,", February 12, 1955 (Box 56)
        - The Scottish Rite Bodies of the Valley of Cleveland, Vesper Hour Service, March 13, 1955 (Box 56)
        - State of the University, March 21, 1955 (Box 56)
        - Alumni, June, 1955 (Box 56)
        - Unidentified Speeches, June, 1955 (Box 56)
        - Detroit, MI, "Football Bust,", November 28, 1955 (Box 56)
        - Conference of Higher Education, December 6, 1955 (Box 56)
        - Alumni Conference, December 9, 1955 (Box 56)
        - TV -- Mission of M., December 28, 1955 (Box 56)
        - Ann Arbor High School Commencement, 1955 (Box 56)
        - Dentistry Alumni, 1955 (Box 56)
        - Michigan Legislature, 1955 (Box 56)
        - Speeches, Michigan/Ohio History, 1955 (Box 56)
        - Unidentified Speech, 1955 (Box 56)
        - Windsor Rotary (Box 56)
      - 1956
        - The America-Japan Society, "The Role of Higher Education in International Relations,", January 20, 1956 (Box 56)
        - Michigan Society of Registered Land Surveyors, February 2-4, 1956 (Box 56)
        - The Kennecott Lecture Series, "Education in the American System,", March 1, 1956 (Box 56)
        - American Association of Colleges of Pharmacy & National Association of Boards of Pharmacy, "Is There Balm in Gilead?", April 9, 1956 (Box 56)
        - New York University Founders Day Address, "Is There Balm in Gilead?", April 27, 1956 (Box 56)
        - State of the University, September, 1956 (Box 56)
        - Mary Washington College, "The Opening of a Door,", October, 1956 (Box 56)
        - Colorado College Inauguration of Louis Tomlinson Benezet, November 2, 1956 (Box 56)
        - Principal-Freshman and Junior College Conference, November 8, 1956 (Box 56)
        - The Sixth Annual Atom Day & Dedication of the Ford Nuclear Reactor, November 16, 1956 (Box 56)
        - Cairo High School Assembly, November, 1956 (Box 56)
        - Ohio Union Ballrooms, Ohio State University, "Learning How to Learn,", December 4, 1956 (Box 56)
      - 1957
        - Detroit Historical Society, "Adventures in History,", January 28, 1957 (Box 56)
        - Toledo Chamber of Commerce, "Higher Education and Business,", February 6, 1957 (Box 56)
        - American Management Association, Chicago, IL, February 14, 1957 (Box 56)
        - World Ideological Conflict sponsored by U.S. Information Agency, "International Cultural Exchanges,", April 12, 1957 (Box 56)
        - Cranbrook School, "The Significance of a Liberal Arts Education Today,", April 13, 1957 (Box 56)
        - Inter-Fraternity Council, Alumni Annual Banquet, Detroit, April 25, 1957 (Box 56)
        - The Ohio Historical Society, "Commerce and Culture, The Pattern in Ohio: An Address,", April 27, 1957 (Box 56)
        - 11th Annual Congressional Dinner, Association Executives of Michigan, "Business, Congress, Education -- Where Are We Going?,", April 30, 1957 (Box 56)
        - Michigan Schoolmasters Club, May 10, 1957 (Box 56)
        - Hiriam College, June 9, 1957 (Box 56)
        - National Federation of Business & Professional Women's Clubs, Inc., "Womanpower -- Its Potential,", July 8, 1957 (Box 56)
        - Michigan Press Club Past Presidents Meeting/Dinner, October 4, 1957 (Box 56)
        - U.N., "The One and the Many,", October 22, 1957 (Box 56)
        - Alumni Speaking Tour, November 5-7, 1957 (Box 56)
        - 11th Conference: Higher Education, November 19, 1957 (Box 56)
        - Evangelical United Brethren Church & First Presbyterian Church, Ann Arbor, Community Thanksgiving Services, "Be Not Afraid Nor Dismayed, By Reason of this Great Multitude,", November 28, 1957 (Box 56)
      - 1958
        - The Commercial Club of Cincinnati, "Business, Government, Education -- Where Are We Going?,", January 18, 1958 (Box 56)
        - The Newcomen Society, "'The University of Michigan': 140 Years from Michigan Wilderness to a World Center of Learning! (1817-1957", January 24, 1958 (Box 56)
        - University of Florida, "The Invisible Sun,", February 1, 1958 (Box 56)
        - Undergraduate Library Dedication Dinner, University of Michigan, "The Invisible Sun,", February 21, 1958 (Box 56)
        - American Association of Junior Colleges, "The One and the Many,", March 7, 1958 (Box 56)
        - Mich Con Gas Co., Ann Arbor, April 2, 1958 (Box 56)
        - Conference of the Michigan High School, "My View of Secondary Schools,", April 10, 1958 (Box 56)
        - Ypsilanti Bd. Of Com., May 27, 1958 (Box 56)
        - University of Michigan Medical School, "Address of Welcome,", June 6-7, 1958 (Box 56)
        - Kalamazoo College Commencement, June 8, 1958 (Box 56)
        - University of Michigan, "Religion in Higher Education in America,", June 24, 1958 (Box 56)
        - American Institute of Architects, Cleveland, OH, "The Western Reserve -- Part of our Heritage,", July 8, 1958 (Box 56)
        - General Motors 50th Anniversary, "Golden Milestone Salute to General Motors,", August 15, 1958 (Box 56)
        - 3rd Biennial Conf. Engr. Ed., October 15, 1958 (Box 56)
      - 1959
        - International Edison Birthday Celebration, Detroit, "Beachheads to Discovery,", February 11, 1959 (Box 56)
        - Development Council, February 14, 1959 (Box 56)
        - 1959 Conference on Legal Education, University of Michigan, "The Law Schools Look Ahead," June 15-18, 1959 (Box 56)
        - Boy Scouts of America, Ann Arbor, "Our Nation's Youth,", September 7, 1959 (Box 56)
        - The Economic Club of Detroit, "Danger in the Red Schoolhouse?,", September 21, 1959 (Box 56)
        - State of the University, October 5, 1959 (Box 56)
        - University Press Club of Michigan Annual Meeting, Theme: Communism and Main Street, U.S.A., "The Educational Challenge,", October 16-17, 1959 (Box 56)
        - Law School Centennial Banquet, "Remarks,", October 23, 1959 (Box 56)
        - National Association of Manufacturers, New York City, "Achieving Social Progress at Home,", December 2, 1959 (Box 56)
      - 1960
        - Dedication of the Mental Health Research Institute Building, Michigan Congress of Parents & Teachers, Ann Arbor, January 29, 1960 (Box 56)
        - Annual Congressional Dinner of University of Michigan Club, Washington, D.C., February 24, 1960 (Box 56)
        - United Negro College Fund, Detroit, April 5, 1960 (Box 56)
        - Bowling Green State University, Golden Anniversary Convocation, "New Responsibilities of the State University,", May 19, 1960 (Box 56)
        - Conference on the Language Laboratory in the Secondary School, Ann Arbor, October 13, 1960 (Box 56)
        - National Association of Schools of Music, Chicago, Illinois, November 26, 1960 (Box 56)
        - National Conference of Christians and Jews, Lou R. Crandall Brotherhood Award Dinner, December 6, 1960 (Box 56)
      - 1961 (Box 57)
        - National Music Camp, "Education for the Gifted Youth,", January 25, 1961 (Box 57)
        - Annual Congressional Dinner of University of Michigan Club, Washington, D.C., February 7, 1961 (Box 57)
        - Churchmen's Banquet, Ann Arbor, March 9, 1961 (Box 57)
        - Arts Symposium, Ohio Wesleyan University, "The Fine Arts in the Colleges and Universities,", March 10, 1961 (Box 57)
        - Eagle Scouts, March 20, 1961 (Box 57)
        - Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Centennial Convocation, "Greetings of the American universities to Massachusetts Institute of Technology on the occasion of the Centennial Convocation,", April 9, 1961 (Box 57)
        - Tulane University Inauguration of President Longenecker, April 15, 1961 (Box 57)
        - Traverse City, Community Leadership type meeting with Regents, May 18, 1961 (Box 57)
        - State of the University, October 2, 1961 (Box 57)
        - Principal-Freshman-Counselor Conference, "The Next Decade at the University of Michigan,", November 2, 1961 (Box 57)
        - Senator Alexander Wiley Testimonial Dinner, Milwaukee, Wisconsin, November 27, 1961 (Box 57)
        - Education Committee of the Michigan Constitutional Convention (Con-Con) Testimony, December 12, 1961 (Box 57)
      - 1962
        - Lakeview High School Dedication, Battle Creek, MI, January 7, 1962 (Box 57)
        - Jackon Whiting & Community Address, January 12, 1962 (Box 57)
        - Michigan Association for Professions Speech, Lansing, MI, February 10, 1962 (Box 57)
        - Annual Congressional Dinner of University of Michigan Club, Washington, D.C., February 28, 1962 (Box 57)
        - Lewis Cass Lecture, "Revolutions of Aspiration,", April 18, 1962 (Box 57)
        - Inauguration of Philip G. Hoffman, University of Houston, April 27, 1962 (Box 57)
        - Henry Ford Community College Dedication, May 20, 1962 (Box 57)
        - University of Illinois Citizen's Committee, "The Role of the Trustee in the Public University,", May 23, 1962 (Box 57)
        - Adrian College Commencement Address, May 27, 1962 (Box 57)
        - Detroit Committee on Foreign Relations, "Venezuela & Peru: How We Ally Ourselves for Progress,", June 12, 1962 (Box 57)
        - The Society of Naval Architects and Marine Engineers Spring Meeting, Duluth, MN, June 22, 1962 (Box 57)
        - Michigan Gas and Electric Associations Annual Meeting, Mackinac Is, June 25, 1962 (Box 57)
        - General Motors Conference for Engineering Science & Education, Detroit, July 20, 1962 (Box 57)
        - State of the University, October 1, 1962 (Box 57)
        - University Press Club, "Challenges and Problems Facing Michigan's Colleges and Universities,", September 28, 1962 (Box 57)
        - Waseda University, Tokyo, Japan, October 21, 1962 (Box 57)
      - 1963
        - Annual Congressional Dinner of University of Michigan Club, Washington, DC, "Investment and Pay-Out,", February 20, 1963 (Box 57)
        - Pennsylvania Military College Commencement Address, June 2, 1963 (Box 57)
        - Kent State University Commencement, August 24, 1963 (Box 57)
        - State of the University, September 30, 1963 (Box 57)
        - National Metal Trades Association, Cleveland, OH, "Industry and Education -- How They Can Help Each Other,", October 9, 1963 (Box 57)
        - Texas Personnel and Management Association, Austin, TX, "The Ivy and the Market Place,", October 25, 1963 (Box 57)
        - Football Bust Remarks, December 2, 1963 (Box 57)
      - 1964
        - The Economic Club of Detroit, "Michigan's Great Unknown...", February 3, 1964 (Box 57)
        - Annual Congressional Dinner of University of Michigan Club, Washington, D.C., February 5, 1964 (Box 57)
        - Alumni Clubs' Legislative Dinner, Lansing, MI, February 12, 1964 (Box 57)
        - 6th Annual First Federal Foundation Awards Program, Jackson, MS, "Salute to Leadership,", February 15, 1964 (Box 57)
        - Ohio State University, "Is There Balm in Gilead?", March 10, 1964 (Box 57)
        - Tuskegee Institute Founder's Day Address, Tuskegee Institute, AL, March 22, 1964 (Box 57)
        - University of Michigan Orientation, "President's Welcome to New Students,", August 27, 1964 (Box 57)
        - School of Music Dedication, September 19, 1964 (Box 57)
        - State of the University, September, 1964 (Box 57)
        - Midwest Antiques Forum, Henry Ford Museum "The Old Northwest: Wilderness to Statehood,", October 12, 1964 (Box 57)
        - University of Michigan Convocation, "The University and its Undergraduates,", November 5, 1964 (Box 57)
        - Leland I. Doan Testimonial Dinner, December 9, 1964 (Box 57)
        - The Voice of America Forum Lectures, "University Contributions for American Business and Industry", 1964 (Box 57)
        - Pittsburgh Foundations Luncheon, "Excellence in Higher Education", 1964 (Box 57)
      - 1965
        - Annual Congressional Dinner of University of Michigan Club, Washington, D.C., "The Great University,", February 3, 1965 (Box 57)
        - Citizens Research Council of Michigan Annual Meeting, Detroit, May 19, 1965 (Box 57)
        - Joint Meeting of Columbus Rotary and Kiwanis Clubs, "The Universities in the Great Society,", May 24, 1965 (Box 57)
        - Operation Bentley (government workshop for high school seniors), Michigan State University, June 30, 1965 (Box 57)
        - State of the University, October 4, 1965 (Box 57)
        - Council for Financial Aid to Education, Chicago, IL, "New Needs and New Opportunities,", November 16, 1965 (Box 57)
      - 1966
        - Tribute to Ralph A. Sawyer, January 10, 1966 (Box 57)
        - Tribute to George Higgins, Miami, FL, January 16, 1966 (Box 57)
        - Annual Congressional Dinner of University of Michigan Club, Washington, D.C., February 8, 1966 (Box 57)
        - Roger W. Heyns Inauguration as Chancellor, University of California, Berkeley, March 25, 1966 (Box 57)
        - French Historical Society, Ann Arbor, April 1, 1966 (Box 57)
        - Alumni Lunch, April 30, 1966 (Box 57)
        - U.S. Bureau of Commercial Fisheries Dedication, May 12, 1966 (Box 57)
        - English Language Institute Anniversary Conference, May 13, 1966 (Box 57)
        - Michigan Junior Classical League Welcoming Remarks, May 14, 1966 (Box 57)
        - Ann Arbor Quarterback Club Senior Athletic Award, May 17, 1966 (Box 57)
        - Southern Illinois University Commencement, "Selected for Service,", June 10, 1966 (Box 57)
        - Medical School Convocation, June 17, 1966 (Box 57)
        - Chrysler Corporation Scholarship Program, June 27, 1966 (Box 57)
        - State of the University, September 12, 1966 (Box 57)
        - Foreign Student Reception, September 17, 1966 (Box 57)
        - Alexander F. Morrison Foundation Lecture to the State Bar of California, Anaheim, CA, September 22, 1966 (Box 57)
        - Water Pollution Conference, Kansas City, "The Great Lakes in Perspective,", September 28, 1966 (Box 57)
        - Industrial Mutual Association Banquet, Flint, MI, October 11, 1966 (Box 57)
        - American Forestry Association, "Communication with our Outdoor Heritage,", November 1, 1966 (Box 57)
        - Canadian-American Relations Seminar, University of Windsor, November 3, 1966 (Box 57)
        - Principal-Freshman-Counselor Conference, "The Challenge of Change in a Growing University,", November 10, 1966 (Box 57)
        - University Senate Meeting, November 28, 1966 (Box 57)
        - Football Bust, November, 1966 (Box 57)
        - Annual Meeting of Akron University Associates, University of Akron, "New Needs and New Opportunities in Higher Education,", December 7, 1966 (Box 57)
      - 1967
        - Cooperative Education Conference, Detroit, "Comments on College Cooperative Education,", January 23, 1967 (Box 57)
        - Tri-University Conference, School of Social Work, February 10, 1967 (Box 57)
        - Annual Congressional Dinner of University of Michigan Club, Washington, D.C., "This Time in Perspective,", February 21, 1967 (Box 57)
        - Union College Founder's Day, "New Dimensions in Graduate Education,", February 23, 1967 (Box 57)
        - Sesquicentennial Alumni Celebration, "The University of Michigan: A Habitation and a Name,", March 4, 1967 (Box 57)
        - Detroit Rotary, "An Idea, An Ideal, and a Commitment,", March 8, 1967 (Box 57)
        - Ann Arbor Chamber of Commerce Annual Dinner Meeting, "Harlan Hatcher's Talk at City of the Year Banquet,", March 23, 1967 (Box 57)
        - School of Music Honors Assembly, "The Fine Arts in the Colleges and Universities,", March 29, 1967 (Box 57)
        - National University Extension Association National Conference, April 23, 1967 (Box 57)
        - Alumni Luncheon, April 29, 1967 (Box 57)
        - 15th Anniversary Dinner for Midland Degree Program in Chemical Engineering, May 4, 1967 (Box 57)
        - Alpena Community College Commencement, May 26, 1967 (Box 57)
        - University High School Commencement, June 9, 1967 (Box 57)
        - Eastern Michigan University Commencement, June 10, 1967 (Box 57)
        - Grand Valley State College Commencement, June 18, 1967 (Box 57)
        - University of Michigan Sesquicentennial Observance, "The University and the Body Politic,", July 13, 1967 (Box 57)
        - University of Michigan English Language Institute Commencement, August 17, 1967 (Box 57)
        - Welcome to Students, August 28, 1967 (Box 57)
        - McInally Lecture, "Introduction & Remarks,", September 14, 1967 (Box 57)
        - Alvin M. Bentley Foundation Scholarship Luncheon, September 16, 1967 (Box 57)
        - Presidents Club, September 22, 1967 (Box 57)
        - State of the University, September 27, 1967 (Box 57)
        - Sesquicentennial Ceremony IV, "The Voices of Civilization,", October 6, 1967 (Box 57)
        - Business Administration -- Alumni Conference & Sesquicentennial Business Conference, October 9, 1967 (Box 57)
        - Alumnae Gift Remarks, Martha Cook Building, October 21, 1967 (Box 57)
        - Canadian-American Relations Seminar, "Welcoming Remarks & Introduction,", November 2, 1967 (Box 57)
        - Karl Haas Inauguration as President of National Music Camp and Interlochen Arts Academy, November 5, 1967 (Box 57)
      - 1971
        - Power Center for the Performing Arts Dedication, October 5, 1971 (Box 57)
        - Undated (Box 57)
        - 63rd Meeting of American Philological Association and Archaeological Institute of America (Box 57)
        - James B. Angell Plaque Unveiling (Box 57)
        - Civilian Club, Detroit, April 14, 1971 (Box 57)
        - Cranbrook 25th Anniversary Celebration (Box 57)
        - Michigan's Mid-Century Program in Higher Education (Box 57)
        - Rotary, Ann Arbor (Box 57)
        - Fair Housing Legislation, University of Michigan (Box 57)
        - Speeches, University of Michigan (Box 57)
    - International Travel
      - Hawaii, Philippines, Hong Kong, Taipei, Japan, December 1955-January 1956; 4 folders (Box 58)
      - Russia, April-May 1959; 4 folders (Box 58)